hello everyone and welcome to ml dawn so
today
we are having an interview with
professor carl frisson uh professor
furson is a theoretical neuroscientist
and a world-renowned authority on brain
imaging
he has invented statistical parametric
mapping or spm which is a software
package designed for the analysis of
brain imaging data sequences and also
i think his main contribution uh to
theoretical neurobiology is the free
energy principle for action and
perception that hopefully we'll get the
time to
also explore
professor frison thank you so much for
for being with us with us today my
pleasure
um okay
um so let's just get started
the free energy principle right
um could you just tell us about what the
free energy principle is and
how has it enriched our understanding of
the brain as a unifying brain theory if
you will
right
so i normally respond to that question
by asking whether you want the sort of
the high road or the low road approach
to um
understanding what the free energy
principle is about um
i'll very briefly try to surmise both so
the low road uh which is like a sort of
bottom-up way of understanding it which
is a kind of way that i think
a lot of
um neuroscientists and psychologists
would understand things or more broadly
people in neurobiology
would be
the denouement
at the present time
of very old and
compelling ideas about the brain as
literally a fantastic organ a an organ
that constructs
hypotheses explanations
fantasies that afford the best
explanation for all the sensory
impressions all the sensory data that we
have to assimilate and literally make
sense of
um
so the principles that underwrite that
perspective
were articulated in various disciplines
by people like kant and helmholtz
department richard gregory nancy spy
synthesis
um perception as hypothesis making
leverage to greater effect in machine
learning with people
like uh jeffrey hinton and peter diane
and the notion of the helmholtzmann sea
machine in turn
borrowing technical ideas from the
physics and engineering literature such
as feynman's free energy principle as a
way of
writing down
a prescription
or a normative account of this kind of
sense making and you end up with a
a formal first principle account of
sense making which you can write down as
a computer program or you can write down
mathematically but essentially
casts the brain
as
in the service of trying to minimize its
variational free energy and you can read
variation free energy here essentially
as a kind of prediction error
technically the free energy gradients
are prediction errorism so what's the
prediction well it's just the difference
between
what given your beliefs about the
current state of affairs out there
beyond the skull-bound brain
what would i expect to see
what would i predict
and then i compare my predictions with
what i'm actually sensing and that
constitutes a prediction error and then
i use the prediction error to drive my
beliefs
in a way that eliminates that prediction
as i got a sufficient account of what's
going on and that's often referred to as
predictive processing
in its inactive form or active inference
and when we're drilling down just on the
perceptual synthesis that is of you know
afforded by this account um the most
popular scheme that i would be
predictive coding sort of the
reciprocal exchange of top-down
predictions from the inside out to the
parts of the brain dealing with sensory
processing
that is complemented by a an ascending
outside in flow of prediction errors
where you need the predictions to form
the prediction errors and then the
predictions or the expectations
they that are generating those
predictions um
um are informed and updated by the
prediction errors technically that's a
process called base in belief updating
hence the bayesian brain and the
helmholtz machine
formulations of it so that would be
an account of the free energy principle
really as a prescription
um
an algorithm
a technological account of a normative
theory for
the brain as an active organ
making sense of data with the key twist
that of course the brain or you and i
are in charge of the data that we're
trying to make sense of there's an added
inactivist twist here it's not just that
we're good
bayesian filters or data assimilators we
actively have to decide what kind of
data we want
to base our inferences upon um
literally in terms of where i was where
i'm going to look next how i visually
palpate the world or you know which news
channels to listen to or which wikipedia
page i'm going to forage next that you
know so that that's possibly more
um more of a difficult problem the brain
has to solve than just simply making
sense of the data but both are bound up
in this um
in this sort of generic account in terms
of free energy minimization or the
explaining away and accounting for
providing the best explanation that
eliminates uh united's prediction errors
very briefly the high road is the kind
of uh approach
um that a physicist would uh take
and you can derive exactly the same
mechanics of belief updating the same
sort of
[Music]
explanation for sentient behavior where
behavior is important because that's the
active part uh just from an analysis of
things that exist in in the sense of
physics and the particular physics here
is the physics of non uh non-equilibrium
steady state
system systems that have
the
the the remarkable property
of returning to states that they were
once in you know mathematically have
attracting sets or characteristic states
of being that you know i
am found at this temperature in this
kind of location and this sort of
environment
so all the things that would
characterize me
represent states that i keep on
revisiting and that can be written down
mathematically in terms of the
dynamical systems theory of attracting
sets and you can work out the
probability distributions or you can
appeal to
fireman's work on path integral
formulations um to work out well if
things exist
then what properties what dynamics must
they have been must they possess in
order to exist
and to maintain themselves in within
these
viable states of being so in the life
sciences this would be known as
autophagus or self-creation in the
computational chemistry of the
self-assembly how do molecules assemble
themselves and retain their sort of
morphology and structural or
configurational um
organization
and it turns out that you end up with
exactly the same equations that you're
trying to you know everything that we do
either on the inside or in terms of
acting upon the world is in the service
of minimizing this
variational
proxy for
prediction error
but also mathematically happens to be
the
quantity that
as
statisticians would try to optimize
namely the marginal likelihood or the
evidence for models of the world so you
get this sort of um
technological account
um that systems that self-organize
look as if they're trying to maximize
the evidence for their models of the
world sometimes people reflect that as
self-evidencing so that would be a
philosophical account of the top-down
physicists explanation for the way that
you and i
actively organize our
exchanges with the lived world in order
to in order to exist to maintain our
existence um some generalized
homeostasis
that can be described mathematically as
a minimization of um variation free
energy
okay uh very very interesting so
as far as i understand uh
so
we are it's about
as you said we're trying to
sort of do actions that would maximize
the probability of our existence of our
model that we have from the the
the environment that we're living in
um so which is i think the same thing
that uh that you refer to as marginal
likelihood yes
the probability of uh observation given
the model that i currently have
um of the of the world
um what i'm trying to understand is
trying to
marry that idea with the with the other
idea that
the brain selects
which kind of which one of these inputs
to consider like how to affect the
environment because when we say the
probability of
my input from my receptors
given the model i have
from from the environment
it is as if i have a control of
what i will necessarily do because i
mean there are so many receptions
coming i might choose to ignore some of
them but then it might not be the right
choice also
when you talk about optimization i
realize that now from
if i look at this from a machine
learning perspective
since we're optimizing could we overfit
i mean
and fail to generalize
okay
well that's a great questions they're
about they're about
um
so first of all just
yeah i am sorry i will use technical um
terms
with with very little theory of mind
because i'm so used to to doing so so
you're absolutely right the marginal
likelihood is nothing magical it's just
the probability that um these sensory
data would be solicited experienced um
under my model of how those data were
generated you're absolutely right the
marginal bit comes from um marginalizing
out over or averaging
over the unknown parameters of a
generative model but we don't need to
worry about that you know the model
evidence is the marginal likelihood
and the logarithm of that is is a
negative free energy um
[Music]
but your more interesting question i
mean if you now um
review well you know this this podcast
um and just listen to the words you use
they're very telling so you talk about
selection that's a great word to use you
also said i
you know so immediately there's a
there's a an inactive a generational
aspect to your question so a predictive
coding scheme that's just assimilating
data and making sense of data has no
notion of of me has no selfhood and
certainly doesn't have any it is not
equipped with the ability to choose and
to select which data it wants to
actually assimilate or to classify or to
categorize so we're going beyond machine
learning now we are going beyond um
simply passively um
in a sort of um outside in way making
sense of data we are now asking about
this really deep question how on earth
do we select the data to assimilate
so
the answer is very simple um
in the same
spirit that um
everything on the inside that's doing
this assimilation has to minimize the
prediction error sometimes cast in terms
of surprise in a technical sense so this
this is if you're an information
theoretician this will be the
self-information um
the
if you're doing that then the natural
question then arises well look what
happens if i'm in control of the data
that i can i can now select or turn
towards
well now
i have to
choose the actions that will produce
data that are have the minimum expected
surprise or the minimum expected
prediction error
so if surprise
which is another word for a mathematical
uh expression for this um
bound on surprise or evidence called
variation free energy
um is
the thing in the moment then after i
have have acted in the future
then what i want to do is to minimize my
expected surprise my expected prediction
error
so what's that well expected surprise is
technically entropy
um
and more anthropomorphically uh this
would be just uncertainty so what you're
doing is if you're
subscribing to the free energy principle
and you now have to choose the best kind
of act or sampling
or selection um
then you would select those actions
that
minimize your uncertainty the resolve
your uncertainty
another way of expressing that
mathematically is that they have the
greatest information gain
that those kinds of data resolve my
uncertainty more than those kinds of
data
so that's a actually
a well-known bayesian principle um and
it's um
often cast in terms of optimal bayesian
design
and has been known um
since the 1950s through the work of
people like lindley
there are well-defined objective
functions
which are simply how much do i shrink my
uncertainty and technically measured in
terms of a divergence mathematically but
you know we just need to know the
information gain is just the degree to
which i i shrink my uncertainty about
states of affairs out there so what that
means is that we are
if we minimize if we choose those
actions or we want to minimize our free
energy then we have to choose those
actions and minimize the expected free
energy which necessarily makes us into
curious creatures
now you were saying to me i don't know
how to do that i don't understand how to
that you do you're a scientist
even if you don't have a phd
every every child and every student and
every every adult
is a curious scientist they want to know
how their world works
either it's your scientific field of
study or if you're a little baby it's
just how your body works you know what
kind of thing is mum is mum
your same kind of thing as me all of
this information um has to be carefully
selected in order to resolve uncertainty
about this hypothesis on that hypothesis
in exactly the same way that you would
design a good experiment so the when you
design an experiment
then you design the experiment to yield
data that are going to be maximally
informative
in relation to your null versus altered
hypothesis so it's exactly the same
principle governs the selection of
natural experiments that we deploy with
our eyes looking over there or looking
over there it's exactly the same
mathematics as the same imperatives and
indeed um you actually see the same
information theoretic constructs
emerging in the visual search literature
in the neurosciences and you can
construe these as salience maps that you
know they score
the
uncertainty reduction the epistemic
affordance of making that select
selecting those data by by looking over
there or by again looking at this
wikipedia page or listening to this news
channel and not that fake news channel
so
it's a great question because not only
does it um
does it make the i think the really
profound point that that curiosity
of all kinds is baked in to the first
principal account of self-organization
that anything that exists must impart be
acting or appear to act look as if it is
acting to resolve uncertainty about the
exchanges with its economic environment
its culture or the visual scene
the visual scene at hand
furthermore
you're talking about action it's you
that's acting
so it's it there's an implicit sense of
of agency that is owned by the artifact
in question so we're now talking about
something that would be necessary
to equip an agent with some
a very elemental selfhood
the third thing it brings to the table
is is really common sensical but it's
it's a i think a very interesting
observation
and that in order to select
this action over that action
then i have to have
a model of the consequences of my action
but the consequences live in the future
which says that your genetic models
now must cover the future
which means that you've got something
that a lot of things in this universe
don't have which is a model of the
future it has temporal depth
so you know that you could apply the
free energy principle to a thermostat
you could apply it to a virus and it
would work perfectly well you could
simulate thermostats and
make a thermostat or simulate a virus
or possibly even construct one
but these kind the genitive models that
you would use
that has to be in place in order to work
out the surprise due to the predictions
generated by that model
um
would not have the temporal depth of the
models that you and i have
so as soon as you talk about selection
you're talking about essentially
selecting a plan of action a course of
action and
that means necessarily rolling out into
the future so your genitive models have
this temporal depth and furthermore
as soon as you entertain the notion that
i could do this or that then there is an
act of selection in play the thermostat
doesn't have that there's only one thing
it can do because it acts in the moment
but you and i are very have a much more
uh a deeper generative model we bring to
the table that allows it now to set
amongst
a series of counter factual courses of
action you can choose what to say next
or not to say anything at all
and in that choice there is an act of
bayesian technically an act of bayesian
model selection or policy selection
so now you've got thermostats that
select provided they have these deep
charity models that sort of free you
from the moment because they're really
about trajectories and paths you know
how we navigate the lived world
and
the about the overfitting thing oh yes
could we overfit yes
actually why don't we over fit maybe
that's the right question that's a good
question uh yeah that was the fourth
clever part of your question but yeah
the reason you don't ever fit in uh and
i'll probably um
if you indulge me i'll answer this from
the point of view of sort of machine
learning um
or statistics so um the answer here um
lies in an understanding of the nature
of
models and their evidence
so the first thing to say is that there
is no true model of the world there is
no
there is a best model in the world and
that's simply the model that has the
greatest evidence but there's no true
model in the world there are you know
they're all there are many many ways of
explaining um um
how
some data for us sensory data um was
generated and you know providing an
account of that all we can do is find
the one that has the greatest evidence
the greatest marginal likelihood the
greatest probability of the data under
that model so we can change the model
and until the model provides or account
gives you the greatest marginal
likelihood
so what is evidence this is the key
point
evidence
is
accuracy minus complexity
which means that to find the model with
the greatest evidence
is to provide an account of these data
in the simplest way possible
and that simplicity underwrites the
ability to generalize in the absence of
that complexity part of the model
evidence
you would certainly overfit
so if you did if you were allowed to use
as many degrees of freedom um as you
wanted with no constraints on that
i know complexity constraints you would
certainly overfit these data so that the
next day's data
would uh not be extendable because you'd
ex you'd fit all the little random
effects and fluctuations in the in the
data at hand so that complexity term is
absolutely crucial
in ensuring that
maximizing model evidence
surprise minimizing free energy all of
these are statements essentially the
same thing
goes hand in hand
with an automatic
penalty on the complexity
that precludes overfitting and it's
really interesting just to sort of
unpack what complexity is here so um on
a um
on a technical account the complexity is
basically the degree to which i change
my mind having seen some data so
technically it's the difference between
some posterior
bayesian beliefs some probability just a
probabilistic explanation
for
some causes of some data in machine
learning this might be called some the
latent states generating unobservable
latent states hidden states
that are generating observable
measurements or observations or sensory
sensory input from our perspective
um
so i've got two
beliefs before we were talking about
this process of dynamically reducing
free energy or minimizing prediction
error as a process of belief updating
that belief updating is literally
updating a prior belief before i see
data into a posterior belief after i've
seen a posteriori after i've seen the
data and the degree to which you have to
move your belief from the prior to the
posterior is a complexity
so it's the degrees of freedom that
you're using up
in explaining the data now if you've got
really good prior beliefs
you don't have to change your mind very
much and therefore you can provide an
accurate account of this data with a
minimal complexity cost because you've
moved your belief updating has been
extremely efficient and minimally
complex
so it is those kinds of high evidence
generative models
that have this complexity penalty in
place that are able to generalize to new
data because you've got the right kind
of priors
so it all goes hand in hand and it's a
really important point you know i don't
know i i'm wondering whether you knew
this already in virtue of the fact you
asked the question but you know
this this this issue is really um
uh
you know a difficult issue uh in
conventional machine learning
because you know if you just look at the
way the field has gone in machine
learning they've gone to sort of big
data you know sort of you know
committing to the the
ideology of you know big data science
with massively over parameterized neural
networks so if you read a neural network
as a generative model certainly in the
context save an auto encoder
then what you're starting with
is an overly parameterized overly
complex genitive model
which can
beautifully explain any given data set
but it's hopeless in generalizing to
another context or or some new data
simply because the complexity is too
high because there are too many
parameters in that model that's only say
connection weights in a in a current
neural network or a convolutional neural
network
variation auto encoder
so
what that leads to then is um
all sorts of problems with sharp minima
that ensue
because you have not put in the the
complexity term um that you can think of
in terms of just occam's principle you
know so occurs principle has to get into
the objective function so if you've got
so the game now it would be to take a
neural network in machine learning say
in deep learning and try and find out
which collection weights or which you
know what architectural aspects of your
your network you didn't need to provide
an accurate account which is actually
the opposite direction of travel from
most of deep learning at the moment
which are aspiring to more parameters
with bigger computers
there's an interesting little twist
there of course that um there are a
number of um
fundamental principles
such as landauer's principle the
jarzinski equality
which
effectively say that information is
energy and energy is information
and in this present context the degree
of belief updating as scored by the
complexity cost
has a thermodynamic cost which means if
you're
recognizing things properly and
selecting the right things to do
properly with the minimum of complexity
you're doing it with the greatest
efficiency so you can measure the
quality of any artifact
any neural network or neuronal network
simply by the amount of energy it has to
expend to exist
so again you're the drive towards high
performance computing is exactly in the
wrong direction what you're looking for
is sort of um
sentient edge computing like devices
based upon a
an evidence maximization or free energy
minimization approach that should do it
um like your brain which would consume
the same energy as a light bulb
as opposed to a power station so that's
a really good question this you know
you know
that has some really pragmatic
engineering um computer engineering and
uh sort of you know um energetics uh
associated with it and
explains to a great extent why you're so
much better than any neural network that
lives on a
a high performance computer
at the moment
the idea of overfitting and over
parameterized models
just reminded me of this paper by
professor
mikhail belkin
um so
it's it's a it's a paper about this
phenomenon
that happens in over parameterized
models called the double descend as
they've called it
now their question was why over
parameterized models
don't overfit
and does why why why they can do why
they can generalize so well and it's an
it's a very interesting paper it was
really shocking to me because we have
this famous uh i mean in machine
learning we have this famous u-shaped
sort of uh you know plot that shows that
okay the more you parameterize your
model
the
the um well the error in the the error
in your in the predictions of your model
keeps going down and down and down and
after a certain point it fails to
generalize so it just keeps going high
and higher and higher and higher now
what they did was they didn't stop there
they kept all
adding more parameters they kept adding
more and more now what happened then was
after a certain point
uh we have a double the a second descend
in the generalization ability
or in the error let's say the prediction
error it again keeps going down and down
and down in some cases
it goes even below the point
where the the minimum of the first
descent it could it could even get to
better generalization and in some cases
no
it the minimum that it could
ever reach would not be as good as the
minimum of the first descent
so they've called this double descend
and i i'm trying to
and didn't happen oh the devil doesn't
always happened based on their
experience they used it with decision
trees they used it with neural networks
and a couple more models i don't
remember exactly what they were
but
um
the id the notion of accuracy minus
complexity
and that being the idea of that being
the reason as to why
uh we don't overfit i'm trying to
uh sort of mix like to have that next to
the idea of
because their their argument was that
when you have
too much too many number parameters
the model sort of goes towards like you
have you have more knobs to control your
search in the hypothesis space
you you inevitably go to
you as if you can you can you can search
better
and then you find
maybe i think they were arguing that you
find simpler solutions i think if i'm
not mistaken
but
how would you marry that idea with the
idea with this
accuracy minus complexity being the
reason of not overfitting
um
right yeah that's a
very question that one okay
so um i think if you think of this um
the problem in terms of um
finding minima in an objective function
landscape
then
that that phenomena of double descent
makes entire sense in the context of
escaping local minima so let's assume
that we've basically got um a difficult
problem say a brittle
dynamical system or a highly non-linear
problem
where the objective function let's
assume it's
either um
a free energy objective function or some
approximation to it um then it's likely
going to have lots of local minima
around
and
your one instance and one particularly
problematic aspect um you know
probably your your your you have in mind
is this notion of sharp minimum other
minima that have very steep sides that
are very difficult to escape from with
any sort of stochastic annealing or any
sort of um device that would sort of
bring you out of that base of attraction
of that sharp minimum
so
the first point to make before i pursue
that analogy and really basically just
reiterate the solution that you you've
actually just just described which is
absolutely correct i mean i'll i'll do
it you know from from
a dynamical perspective um the first
point to make is that
the failure to
put the complexity term into the
objective functions used by typically by
lots of vanilla machine learning not all
i mean high-end uh um variation auto
encoders use exactly the variation free
energy um or which is um in machine
learning known as an evidence lower
bound or an elbow that is exactly the
same um
objective function we're talking about
um
but those
um those
algorithms that don't do that and just
try to maximize
the likelihood as opposed to the
marginal likelihood so you know just try
to maximize the accuracy such
as scored by the sum of squared
residuals for example so they're
forgetting about the complexity and
they're just drawing down the accuracy
part of it to create these kirin is
sharp minima
the reason that these mineral are sharp
is that the complexity term
creates it into a u-shaped minimum
and this is if you like one expression
occurs principle that the good the good
the good explanations
have to allow for some latitude um so
the curvature of the minima
scores
the
the latitude you have
in the sense that you're not committing
to a very particular explanation that
provides an accurate account of these
data
there are a number ways of understanding
this one of them is in fact from the
point of view of uh james's maximum
entry principle that under constraints
afforded by say a likelihood and
surprise on a generative model
the best explanation is always the
belief that has the maximum entropy
which is means it has the minimum
curvature in some
free energy landscape so the free energy
functional
provides an objective function where all
the minima are flat thereby eluding the
sharp minimum problems that
plagues most conventional machine
learning so i think that's the first
thing to recognize that you will find
those free energy minima
um more efficiently provided you can
escape the local minima simply because
the free energy minima are always flat
and then they're less likely to trap you
um so let's now take what
what are what other ways uh could you
escape
sharp minima um that are local minima
that are high in a free energy landscape
so just
so one sort of picture i use for my
students is is very much like a mountain
range um that is the genesis of a little
stream that turns into a river so the
lower you get in the landscape the wider
the rivers
the shallower the valleys until
ultimately you get to an estuary and so
exactly the same sort of if you like um
landscape exists in a free energy
operational free energy concept context
so stuff high up uh you know
all the sharp minima that have a very
undesirable high free energy um are the
rust stuff in the higher mountains and
your job is to get down uh flow down to
the nice shallow
um global minima that are much that have
this um this sort of maximum entropy
occurs principle um shallowness to them
with no curvature
so how might you want to get out of
those high
hanging valleys those those sharp minima
well you you've said it basically
if you imagine from the point of view of
dynamical systems theory
flows on a um on a manifold or a um in
this instance a free energy landscape
let's imagine we just got one parameter
to play with so and we've
found ourselves in a v-shaped
minima
and we can't get out of it
but if i add another dimension and now
make my one-dimensional
um objective function two-dimensional
then i can change that fixed-point
attractor that corresponds to the point
of the minimum the local minimum in
question into a subtle point into an
unstable fixed point and i can escape
from it so now i've got a saddle point
where there are now roots away from that
local minimum because as you keep on
adding dimensions i.e adding parameters
to your model the opportunities for
converting a stable fixed point which is
a local minima into an unstable fixed
point from which you can escape
increases geometrically only supremely
so i think that's the explanation
in conversation with people in machine
learning uh and i enjoyed one such
conversation with people
um at nyu just a couple of weeks ago i
i think that that is is probably the
story that you would tell to account for
this sort of throwing lots and lots of
parameters
um at a model
just to destroy stable fixed points that
constitute a local minima so that you
can access the global minima and then
once you've done that you then prune
away all the parameters that you use as
your escape routes to get back to the
simple model so what we're talking about
i think this double dissenting is a
really lovely notion
and it does remind me a little bit of
how the brain works in the sense that
you know it starts off with an overly
parametrized um genitive model so babies
and children actually have more
connections they have more w's um more
um
external connections white matter tracts
than uh than adolescent something you
and i do so you get this progressive
pruning as you grow older so you start
off with this overly parameterized
overly complex
virgin
tablaraza where you can escape all the
local minima and then as time goes on
you then do your pruning
and reduce the number of parameters or
collection uh connection weights in your
in your model to to simplify to to uh in
accord with james's max venture
principle outcomes principle uh from the
point of view the free energy
minimization it's the complexity part of
the minimization so you now get a
smaller parameter model
but you've only done the second wave of
descent if you like after you've escaped
all the local minima by having an overly
parameterized model so i'm sure that
that's you know
this must be a universal principle that
i suspect is so universal it has been
discovered by evolution uh you know
millions of years ago yeah yeah
that was that was amazing wow that was a
totally different perspective that the
the i mean the reduction in the number
of parameters as you grow old i i i
never thought about that first of all i
didn't know that but it was it was
really amazing yeah well it has its
penalties because i am much older than
you and therefore i am much sparser and
wiser than you but i could not adapt to
a new world so i can't go bungee jumping
or go to disco oh my god
wow
wow wow
mind boggling i i don't know what to say
that was that was really enlightening
actually
um so it seems to me that uh there are
two methods of learning in general when
it comes to biological systems
so i did a little bit of research on
this i don't know whether i'm right or
or not but
i could narrow this down to two general
methods
one is perceptual inference
where and the other one is through
action inference now the perceptual
inference i i suppose is when you
generate a model from the world and
you keep updating that the parameters
whereas the action one is you actually
choose actions
um so i know we've discussed this
a little bit at the beginning of the
interview but could you explain
these two methods in more detail and
uh
and compare them as to
it in what situation
am i learning through perceptual
inference and in what situation do i
choose to learn through action inference
right yeah it does i think speak to this
issue of sort of um
machines with agency that we were
talking about before artifacts that have
sentient behavior so the sentient part
would be the sexual inference and the
behavior would be the active inference
and i think that they you know once you
think about sort of artifacts that do
actively exchange with the world i think
they both have to go hand in hand so um
i you know i think it's
although
another excellent question i will
qualify
my answer after i've given you the
vanilla answer which is you know these
are
this is just a joint optimization
process over two kinds of unknowns two
kinds of latent states out there that
generate data
one kind of latent state is the latent
states over which i have no control so
this would be the standard data
simulation classification problem
recognition problem i am given some data
and i have to classify learn its causal
structure infer the particular state
generating latent state generating these
data in this particular context so that
would be perceptual synthesis perceptual
inference and learning the parameters
of that gender model i would call
perceptual learning so in my world i
distinguish between fast processes that
infer time dependent states
and slow processes that infer the
parameters that underlie the
contingencies and the laws um we would
be learning in the machine learning
center so that the w is in a neural
network but the states of the network at
any one point in time i would interpret
as imprints um you know this is the
activity of these nodes and therefore
i'm seeing this kind of face
so that's one set of unknowns but
there's another hugely important set of
unknowns latent states out there those
which i can control
those which i have some agency over so
if i make this movement or i secrete
this or i switch on this knob then the
states out there will also change
if that's the case then you're now
conditioning a certain set of hidden
states
on
latent states which can be thought of as
plans or control variables so the you
know
sort of uh
standard machine learning treatment
so these control variables or uh say in
cultural
theory
now play a really important role because
the transitions the dynamics amongst the
latent states um that are controllable
are now conditioned upon this u but this
u is another random variable
this means i have to infer two sets of
random variables i have to infer the
latent states over which i have no
control
and i also have to infer
the
control variables if you like the plans
um upon which the variables the states
that i do have control over are
conditioned so there's two kinds of
inference here which you can think of in
terms of the distinction between someone
just applying a kalman filter to
estimate the states of some plant
versus um estimating the best thing to
do if you you were doing applying
control theory and you know when you're
controlling a particular plant say in
engineering
but because we're now committed to
understanding everything in terms of
optimizing
a free energy functional of beliefs or
probability distributions that now
becomes that that planning or control
theoretical part of the problem the
active influence part of the problem now
becomes planning as inference
so
you know in a sense you can read
the two perceptual and active sides of
imprints
as really the same process
working hand in hand in parallel
but acknowledging there are two
different kinds of variables that you
you you have to infer you have to work
out basically
what's the state of affairs out there
and what am i doing about it
and then of course you can see now that
the active infant side the um the
planning as inference now has to
consider a number of plausible plans and
then we get back to selecting the um the
most likely plan which minimizes the
expected free energy or results which is
uncertainty or avoid surprising outcomes
like you know um
your your machine crashing if you're in
an autonomous driving uh
situation so you can write in uh all
your prior preferences into that um
expected free energy in the future
conditioned upon the plan
so
i would i would say that that term uh
that sort of you know there is no choice
to do
active inference means that you have to
infer both the latent states of the
world and the way that you're
intervening and uh on those states
through controlling state transitions
that just means planning as imprints
that's part and parcel of
active influence and just being and
being um existing in a world that you're
continually sampling and it's
continually generating data for you to
make sense of there's you know there's a
circular causality there
the the the the sort of
the twist here
um the qualification
is that i think you're absolutely right
that in fact we do switch between that
active and perceptual inference in
reality so
if i was building an artifact i probably
wouldn't worry about what i'm about to
say but if i want to describe you and me
i would describe you and me
as basically machines
that are built to
um in a saltatory way in an intermittent
way
alternatively
plan an action and execute it
and then gather some data and then
make perceptual inferences or you know
do the perceptual learning side of
things so i mean this in the sense that
um the way that we the temporal
scheduling and the alternation between
the action and the
the perception of the active inference
and the perceptual inference
the way that it seems to be scheduled
and organized in biological artifacts
like like ourselves
is that every 250 milliseconds about
four times a second
we act
and
within those
actions
we do our perceptual synthesis so this
you'll see this yo
for example
every 250 milliseconds about four times
a second you will move your eyes with
cyclic eye movements so you're you're
getting little snapshots every 250
milliseconds at four hertz
um and during the acquisition during the
action you actually switch off your
sensory channels it's called sarcanic
suppression
if you're an engineer you're basically
turning the kalman gain down to zero
when you're doing the action bit
so you don't see the optical flow
induced by your eye movements you just
don't see that what you see is the thing
that you've actually fixated on and you
you uh
you use that to construct a scene you
assimilate you build you build up your
this illusion that the you know there's
a visual c down there but in fact in
reality that in little snapshots from
here and here at about four hertz
the way that you speak if you think
about or just listen to me and the way
that you you hear things um well that's
not quite the truth certainly the way
that you um you
fulfill your proprioceptive predictions
during speech all my phonemes are
roughly 200 milliseconds long so i'm
just producing a second you know a
discrete sequence of little packages of
phonemes every 250 milliseconds
if i was a mouse
i would sample
sample my world by whisking my whiskers
and the frequency of that is 250
milliseconds or four hertz and if you
now look at the belief updating
um
on the inside which would correspond to
the perceptual inference making sense of
the data sampled by my whisking around
my burrow
and you see again this profound theta
rhythm that dominates the active
exploration of the environment
that within it is nested all the fast
perceptual belief updating usually at
what's called a gamma frequency about 40
hertz so you've got this lovely
separation of time skills where we make
a move on the world
at
your four times a second we get some
data and then we quickly process what
that means
when we've reached a conclusion then we
go off and get the next bit of data and
then we process this
so for artifacts like you and me
um there is actually i think a temporal
separation
of the active part and the the
perceptual part
part of inference so i'm waiting to see
until they build that into robots
because i think you can very realistic
um behaviors and the way that people
respond to things and you know orientate
to things or understand things through
this sort of discretization or quantity
quantization of discrete packets of
information that live within say you
know a few hundred milliseconds and you
know and that dictates the type of
scheduling of at least biological uh
belief updating
wow
unbelievable
that was amazing so it it feels like
there is no parallelization there is
actually very fast switching between the
two
um
like a joint optimization yes
just require you know if i was building
a computer i wouldn't do that it's just
that obviously there's a better way of
doing it an evolution has found that
this sort of uh this fast switching is
the best way to do it in the to explain
the kinds of worlds in which we live in
we are where biological motion has
certain time constants were you know
meteorological events or things around
us changing a certain time scale it's
clearly the most efficient way uh you
know according to evolution anyway oh
basically oh yeah
absolutely wow that was amazing so uh so
we we keep we kept talking about active
inference and
of all the actions that i
could choose i'm choosing the one that
on average would maximize or say
minimize surprise in future or minimize
free energy
i'm trying to think as to so first of
all it it requires
i suppose i don't know whether the word
is my wording is right or wrong but
some sort of a knowledge about the
future as you said it requires look into
the future
um i can't help but notice
that there is a similarity between
active inference and reinforcement
learning
however in reinforcement learning what
we do is we have the ultimate we like we
have an end goal and end state and we
just let the machine
do whatever it's it wants to do round
like exploration exploitation whatever
it wants to do
many many many times
so eventually it has a way to back
propagate the expected reward to the
current state
but
a human being
that say it's experiencing something for
the first time
and wants to choose the action
i
i don't it doesn't have that that that
option
right
so
first of all how would you differentiate
between active inference and
reinforcement learning and
second of all
um
[Music]
let's let's just discuss as i forgot the
the second question uh let's just
discuss the first the difference between
active inference and uh reinforcement
learning yeah i relieve because that's a
very big question
but feel free to prepare the next one
while we're well we're dealing with okay
perfect
so um there are a number of ways of
answering that question and the simplest
way of course this is to look
at what is on the tin when you pick up
active inference versus reinforcement
learning one's about inference and one
is about learning
so
active inference has an
influence and learning which has the
important consequence that you have um
beliefs not just about the um states of
the world but also beliefs about the
parameters of your genetic model so it
comes equipped with beliefs about the
w's in say a neural network
reinforcement learning is just about
learning the parameters you could look
at reinforcement learning um as a
mechanism
to
enable machines to learn to infer and in
part i think that's how people often um
understand inference in the context of
machine learning and strictly speaking
the optimization process is applied to
the weights the parameters of a
generative model the contingencies so
there's um
there's one fundamental difference
between reinforcement learning and
active inference in the context of
belief updating
i don't think that's quite the spirit of
your question though so i think
another way of looking at the difference
between active inference and
reinforcement learning
is just in terms of the tediology and
asking what is it that you want to
optimize so reinforcement learning you
assume the existence of a reward
function or loss function a cost
function a value function and then you
optimize your neural network or your
your artifact um to um respond to any
given um either explicit state or
inferred state with a particular action
the and that action is chosen by the
nationality principle to maximize the
expected reward
so that presupposes existence of a a
value function um and if that exists
then by the optimality principle you can
then events a an optimal state action
policy
is that um
is it can that be um
if you like
framed in terms of active imprints the
answer is yes but as a very very special
case
so what is that special case well it's a
special case
where you can reduce
um
the
the function
that is implicit in active inference
which is a functional of belief so
remember your planning as inference
belief updating in terms of perceptual
inference and and
data assimilation evidence accumulation
and all that good stuff kalman filtering
and the action selection via planning as
inference this is inference so the
objective function is a functional
function of a function or a functional
and that function is a belief so the
objective function in active inference
is uh belief based
so under what conditions could you
actually reduce an active inference
formulation of a problem to a bell to
the kind of problem the optimality
principle would apply was when you
shrink your belief
down to have zero uncertainty so if you
take uncertainty off the table
then you can get back to a effectively a
um
the
situations in which you can apply the
bell but optimality principle
interestingly just for your
entertainment the way that you do that
technically is just by
describing your reward as a log prior
probability of
some outcome that you prefer so we often
call it a prior preference so we say
that every outcome um is equipped with a
reward or a loss function so instead of
having two separate channels sensory
information and reinforcement
information we simplify the problem and
say no every output every observation or
sensory input comes labeled
with a rewarding aspect so your reward
function now
becomes very high dimensional and
continuous
and
it's just basically the long probability
of a priori
me something that outcome
and once you write that down and you
take away uncertainty um then you can
apply the beveled optionality principle
so you can look at reinforcement
learning as a special case of active
inference when there's no uncertainty
the problem with doing that though
is if there's no uncertainty that means
that the curiosity part
of the objective the expected free
energy
is zero
which means you've lost the opportunity
now to simulate artificial curiosity and
exactly the kind of sentient behavior
that we were talking about half an hour
ago
because there is no information to be
gained there is no information seeking
at hand because you know everything why
do you know everything well because my
in my model of the world in my
reinforcement learning model of the
world there is no uncertainty i know
everything i can see all the hidden
states or at least i can infer them um
so
the the the the what you lose by
converting a an objective function which
is a function of beliefs which is you
know the
variational free energy or the marginal
likelihood or the model evidence all of
these are usually logarithms of or kl
divergences or free energy functionals
of probability distributions beliefs
if you now try to you know coerce that
into a function of states as opposed to
beliefs about states you take away all
the epistemics you preclude any proper
discussion or treatment or account of
artificial curiosity in your robotics
this would be intrinsic motivation so um
you know the the
the intrinsic value the value of
information the epistemic value
of making that move what would happen if
i did that has its own if you like
epistemic reward
but that part of the reward function
also more explicitly not part of the
expected free energy uh or the expected
evidence or the expected uh surprise
and that part has um
has been removed when you dispense with
or you you you try to cast the um
the problem um in terms of the bellman
optimality principle just a little
technical interesting technical twist
here
um
when you um when you consider the full
problem where you're dealing with um
functionals or probability distributions
for us bayesian beliefs
um you are technically dealing with um
usually path integrals because you as
we've spoken about before you know our
paths go into the future and so the plan
has
has a trajectory or a path into the
future so now you've got a path integral
of a functional of a log
basically a long probability which is an
energy so you've got a path interval of
an energy which is called an action and
you're trying to minimize expected free
energy which is this
this action so all you're saying is that
i can explain sentient behavior
with hamilton's principle of least
action
so now you're replacing the bellman
optimality principle
which applies to value functions of
states
with
hamilton's principle of least action
which um
deals with if you like value functionals
or belief states or beliefs about about
states so that's for me how i would see
that there's a fundamental difference
between reinforcement learning and
active inference but it's not a
difference that should be overly
celebrated in the sense you can get from
one to the other you can repair that
dialectic if you like as long as you're
prepared to take all the reduceable
uncertainty out of the game
or off the off the table
does that is that a
kind of yeah
yeah yeah um i'm trying to understand
one bit of this um
so when you say that in reinforcement
learning we actually know there's
certainty
in reinforcement learning sometimes
we're not aware of the world i mean like
many things could happen that could like
you know
put obstacles on
on the path of our agent that could
happen but then the agent somehow learns
to you know get out of them
um i i don't get the idea of
not having uncertainty and reinforcement
learning
i didn't get that part to say that there
is no uncertainty in reinforcement
learning would be
disingenuous and
and
i i think profit possibly for me most
easily understood in terms of
reinforcement learning um
being one application of
bayes optimality in the context of
optimal basic decision making with a
loss function so it's really it was
really the nature of the loss function i
was talking about what i was trying to
get across was that um bayesian decision
theoretic approaches
don't have as part of the loss function
any reduction of of uncertainty so you
have to build that in by hand so that
novelty bonuses or exploration bonuses
and things uh so you have to apply all
sorts of widgets or little tricks to to
make your own your
your loss function even treated under
uncertainty you know in a basic decision
theoretic context or say a partially
observed market decision process
you have to actually write in what you
get for free if you start with an
expected free energy or unexpected um
marginal likelihood um
so it's it's a kind of uncertainty that
matters in terms of what i believe i was
talking about so
you know
it's it's a difference between um uh you
know a neural network
that's trying to be on target uh for as
much time as it can
in a noisy uncertain situation for
example
and a neural network
that knows it doesn't know certain
things that would enable it to find out
what
what what particular times it should be
from the target or from what particular
direction because there are certain
unknowns out there that it can actually
resolve with particular epistemic moves
that have this intrinsic value of this
intrinsic motivation
um that give it this curious aspect so
it contextualizes the optimal bayesian
decision theory
exactly by adding in the optimal basic
design principle we're talking about
before which is this
which is this sort of uh information
seeking aspect so the the full picture
from my perspective of the perspective
of the free energy principle
is that
that you would you can decompose the
objective function expected free energy
into two parts literally linearly um
into into you know an epistemic part
and as a reward or pragmatic part
and that's the epistemic part that
disappears when you
go straight for optimizing the reward
function or the uh or the
your prime beliefs there's an
interesting intermediate case um
which you can get out just by
rearranging certain terms in the um in
the excited free energy functional which
is um kl control so this would be like
risk sensitive control
so
so i'm not sure whether you put this
under reinforcement learning or not um
so i'd have to ask you but so from my
point of view this is a an interesting
middle ground
where you've now
included um
uncertainty about the consequences of my
action
into the game so instead of now just
trying to maximize the expected utility
of the expected loss function on the
expected reward under some belief about
the consequences of action i'm now um
going to minimize the kl divergence or
the difference between
what i think will happen the outcomes
that i under my posterior predicted
density
technically but more intuitively what i
think the outcomes will be if i take
this plan or this course of action
and then i have this
set of preferences you know that encode
my preferred outcomes and then i just
choose the action that minimizes the kl
divergence between the two so this has
uncertainty um in it um that is not
quite the full info
uncertainty reduction but it certainly
accommodates a degree of uncertainty um
when it comes to real world applications
uh again um i'm thinking about sort of
engineering applications in control
theory where this will be known as kl
cultural and economics it's called risk
sensitive control so that would be like
a finessed reinforcement learning value
maximizing scheme that has gotten
uncertainty banked into it and you know
that's an interesting um
uh halfway house between the sort of
vanilla expected utility which i'm
reading as a reinforcement learning
process possibly unfairly um
and the full um the full size of active
inference um expected free energy it's a
really great game if you have time in
terms of just
writing down the you know the
probability distributions and then and
just rearranging them to different kinds
of divergences and just trying to read
them as if you're an economist or you're
a
an engineer control theoretician or or
you're a behavioral psychologist
reinforcement learning or your neuro
roboticist developmental neuro
roboticist trying to understand
intrinsic motivation but by switching
them around you can get all sorts of
interesting different perspectives on
this
overall um you know expected surprise
minimization uh like objective function
i see oh that was really amazing so we
talked about perceptual inference and
active inference now both of those ideas
highly rely on the environment one is
modeling the environment
and the other one chooses actions that
would you know
maximize
the the probability of my existence
now both of them rely on the environment
but what about when we come up with some
abstract knowledge that never existed
before
like the first time that someone thought
about
the wright brothers thought about
an airplane or the first time some
someone thought about a mermaid
um so anytime that something if that's
even possible i don't know the first
time that something jumps into one's
mind that never has existed in the
environment
and they they try to make it into like
create it
into reality
can we explain that part the
knowledge generation
with with these two ideas uh active
inference or perceptual inference
yeah again another very challenging
question um i i would contend that you
can so i think you're touching now upon
sort of
the links between the mechanisms of um
um the underwrite
model optimization and to say curiosity
but more i think the notions of
creativity and exploring different model
spaces
so we're now moving
in fact actually completely away from
active inference and perceptual
inference in terms of um
optimizing both the states and
parameters of a generative model
as it is exposed to data and now turning
to a third level of optimization which
would be the optimization of the model
in and of itself
so
in various fields this will be known as
structural learning for example in
medical and uh constructivism the
problem of not they're saying forget
about let's assume we've got the perfect
scheme if you give me a neural network
or a generative model and
a particular environment that can
generate data i can do all the good
inference uh or learning to infer um
actively and all the canada's inference
and so we've got this little agent now
um coupled exchanging with their or her
environment um
in in in a base optional way
now we move to
a next level hierarchy speaking of an
optimization or free energy minimizing
process which is now not applied to the
parameters of the model but to the model
itself how many hidden layers how many
connections do you use rectified linear
or sigmoid trans you know how do you
carve things up in terms of not just
hierarchical levels but in terms of
know factorizing or modulating modules
or clinician dependencies at any level
all sorts of fundamental structural
issues
that you would practically have to deal
with and contend with when writing down
the architecture of your
neural network that you know will read
as as the structural form of your
genetic model so this
structure learning problem and
from the point of view of a statistician
is a bayesian model selection problem
and it's basically integrating the
marginal likelihood over all the kinds
of data that you could see or all the
kinds of data that you have seen and
then you choose the model
that best accounts for
that has the greatest evidence
so now this is a categorical active
selection of selecting the best model
and i use those words because this is
mathematically i think an apt
description of natural selection so
natural selection and evolution is just
nature's way of doing bayesian model
selections is selecting
the hypothesis namely the phenotype
um where evolution thinks that this
particular hypothesis is a good fit to
me the clinician that i am supplying um
and therefore the econis then selects
the phenotype
through this process of the structural
form of the epigenetically specified for
example um structure of the gelatin
model
um and as soon as you think of it like
that then then um there's a big question
and the big question is well how do you
explore the model space
because we've just said when you're
doing this bayesian model selection
after you've acquired the data
so now what kinds of model spaces would
you would you explore
and
is it necessary to explore there is an
argument which we actually touched upon
earlier on that we can actually start
off with a completely over parameterized
model and prune it so this is a kind of
basic model selection
technically called basic model reduction
where you just literally if i remove
this parameter of this connection from
this model or this hidden layer from
this model
would i have um would i increase its
the pathogram of its uh of its evidence
um in other words um would i be would i
be minimizing complexity without
sacrificing too much accuracy
with the kinds of data that this model
is
is fitted to explain
so you know you could argue that
both the model expansion typically dealt
with
in amazing context through
non-parametric bays so by having
expandable models and priors of the way
that you would add in
different parts or chunks so for example
in a hierarchical dirichlet process you
might have some sort of stick breaking
process on top of that which says you
know can i
am i
is it justified to bringing the new
hidden later variable or you know sort
of uh
in my uh
dirichlet
distribution uh and you'd ask that
question by basically um evaluating the
evidence for that model or the
variational free energy um with or
without that extra bit and if it
improves by adding complexity which more
than pays its way in terms of the
accuracy then you keep it if not you
wouldn't but you you know what the what
the stick breaking process brings to the
table is is a principled way of
expanding or growing the model
i repeat in the context of
non-parametric basing approaches but i
think you can also you can also sorry i
think that both
model expansion
um
and i'm reading that at the moment in
terms of um non-parametric base um
or from the point of view of natural
selection um having recombinations of
certain sort of codes um or
parameterizations of
of um you know
of of genitive models that you can think
of in terms of split emerge like
operations that you get in genetic
recombination
ways of exploring a model space in a
principled structured way or and the
basal model reduction i think both can
be seen um
as the processes that give rise to
creativity and insight and aha moments
um
so um i'm i'm saying that are using some
of the notion of aha moments and
creativity um in um deliberately
just to make the point that some
creative acts are actually acts of
reduction it's not so much the fact that
no one's ever seen this before um sorry
no one has ever represented or um
had this um
you know
this um
object in mind before it's just that no
one's seen that connection before and
that
it's actually a simpler way of viewing
things so if you just think about the
most creative
ideas and signs they are not actually
more complicated de novo constructs they
are simplifications that make sense of
lots of other things in fact they are
instances of the free energy principle
itself providing a simple account
of uh but accurate accounting of
everything
so it's really the the simplification
and the reduction the increase in the
evidence when you suddenly see the two
things that you separately represented
in say two parts on your network can
actually be represented by the same
thing
and you do that by removing it to the
model so actually many apps of creation
uh certainly in sort of minimalist art
forms um are actually getting to the
bare essentials of what's going on again
in um you know in compliance with
occam's principle and you know um
you know um
advertising the complexity cost of
explanations from for the lived world
that that seems to me you know an
important bucket of creative acts is
actually just seeing the structure
underneath it's simply the simplicity
explaining everything with just one
canonical platonic like um
dynamic or construct or narrative or or
sort of factorization however you want
you want to um however you want to um
articulate it and in that sense the
first person to have that simple insight
that oh it's just one of those this is
just one of those the first person is
really the genius and the creative
person but they haven't created anything
new they've just seen something simpler
uh i see um
and in a sense you know that's i think
that's the scientific process that's
exactly why we're having this
conversation that's what you do with
your world so what i do with my life and
i guarantee what you do with your life
it's this journey of finding the
simplest explanation for everything that
we
that we experience uh and you know
leaving it as a legacy you know
speaking to the uncultured aspects of uh
or um
that one could uh appeal to to answer
your question uh for the next the you
know my children or my students or
whatever so you know that's i think the
most that's one way of looking at
creativity
the an interesting point that
ensues from that is that um
you know it is perfectly possible
to be the first art sentient artifact
to see that simplicity
um that is actually in the real world so
it's not the question really of making
new things that aren't out there they've
probably already been out there it's
just you're the first person to have uh
to be able to infer them in that simple
kind kind of way
the other point to make here of course
is well is it really out there well
probably not this is your simplest
explanation it comes back there is no
true model it says this is the best
explanation for what's going on so you
may be the first person to find this
simple explanation um for what's going
on so i would put most of um most of art
and creativity in that in that bracket
but then you compress me on music for
example and and
you know why is why is music so
attractive and well that would be
another question maybe okay yeah
questions yeah perfect um
so
that was amazing actually professor i
was watching one of your talks actually
it was 3 a.m as i was watching that and
you said something that i mean my mom
was sitting next to me and you said
something that it was so interesting
that i i it was like i got a nervous
tick or something then my mom asked me
what happened i said
he said something amazing and i just
want to share that with you and just
maybe we could dig a little bit deeper
in this
um you said something along the line if
i'm if i'm putting this correctly
that
the way our biological neural network
forms itself
tells us something about the environment
that we're living in
in other words
show me your
nervous system then i'll tell you about
the environment you're living in
and it's fascinating to me because maybe
um a couple months months earlier i was
discussing this this gap between
artificial neural networks and
biological neural networks and i was
asking my friends that these distances
like why these axons are long or why not
or these dandruff
we never
sort of
create those
structural uh foundations into our
artificial neural network it seems like
very simplified version of those what do
the what do those features entail really
and when i
heard the piece that you just said in in
that in that talk it was just amazing
now impres and you mentioned the idea of
action in the distance and how
light you know reflects into our eyes
and
at that how that's how we have long
neural you know connections in our like
reflection of action the distance
now in practice
if we actually see like actually in in a
literal meaning if we actually see a ner
the nervous system of an of a biological
being
how much can we really say about the
environment like is it really possible
to to say okay probably it has these
rules it has gravity it has whatever is
it really possible
yes that was a lovely story
more interesting than my answer yes yes
i think it is you know you've just
convinced your listeners it is possible
um have you given some of my favorite
examples but i'll give you a couple more
just to reinforce the point you're
making uh i think the first thing
there's a couple of things before i um
get into this uh
you know you were noting that the
architectures that um have emerged in
neural network theory and machine
learning and naturally deep learning
have a very simple architecture that is
if you like that is inherited from
neural networks
and that's a good thing so remember
simplicity is good and inheriting from
neural networks if you want your
machines to deal with the kinds of
things that human beings deal with those
are two good things they may be a bit
too simple but i think there are certain
architectural features that you can
actually spot which actually would allow
you to apply your law that you've just
suggested give me a neural network and
i'll give you the world that that neural
network is fit to explain or act for um
that law
is um
another law um
from ross ashby we mentioned the law of
requisite variety before the context of
natural selection um but he um with
colleagues also formulated the good
regulated theorem so i'm not sure
whether whether you're probably too
young you're far too young to remember
this this is this is um
was taught as one of the fundaments of
the inception of cybernetics you know
in the early 19th 20th century so the
law
the good regulator theorem which you can
you can wiki there's a wiki little wiki
page or basically what it's saying
is that if any artifact and from from
ashby's perspective this would be
something called a homeostat which has
all this sort of you know regulatory uh
aspects to it that we talked about it if
it regulates its environment basically
it does the right kind of active
inference and
controls the latent states out there the
right kind of way to survive
then it must be a good model of that
environment so he was uh and he
purportedly or thought that he could
prove that and i thought you know i i've
read the paper way where he proves it
it's not an easy read but
if you have a
3am in the morning with nothing else to
do you should try and read it it's
original fruits
let's see see if you're convinced um
but the key point is that this is a very
old idea um and probably you know a very
true idea that
anything that um exists um
in some kind of generalized synchrony
with its economics environment its heat
bath its world it's uh um climate
uh must effectively be a um
be a good model of that climate which
simply means that the architecture the
structure that we're referring to in
terms of structure learning
must in its function in its structural
form recapitulate the causal structure
of what's out there so the structure of
the generative model um will tell you an
enormous amount about the you're the
kind of world that is generating the
sensations that are being used to do the
planning as inference to control that
particular world so
lots of great examples you've given one
well i think one of the most interesting
ones which is why is the brain
why does it have an architecture that
involves
long thin communications at a distance i
mean the liver doesn't and the liver
does a wonderful job of doing its job
and presumably complies with the free
energy principle and doing its own kind
of active imprints in a world of
chemicals and metabolites
so
you you you've given you've given
the viewers the answer it's just that
that must imply
a certain kind of conditional dependency
that has this long-range action at a
distance
and of course we unlike um thermostats
and worms and viruses really have to
live in a world where there is actually
a distance in the sense that i can hear
you from dublin i can see you from
across the room now viruses worms and
thermostats can't do that they are they
their world is is you know is much more
immediate and just relies upon the
conditional dependencies that are
related to the juxtaposition in
symmetric space but we live in a much
more complicated world that has this
action at a distance that that actually
is necessary to explain the kind of
sensations that we that we have to
explain particularly sort of vision and
and audition conveyed by waves of one
sort or or another or another sort
um so i think that's a wonderful example
but you can go even further and sort of
course the grain you know you just look
at the brain and it's and it has two
hemispheres that tells me immediately
that the embodied world of this
particular brain has a bipedal symmetry
yeah so you know if the world includes
the body
then i can tell you almost immediately
that the kind of creature you dissected
this brain from um
the part of the world which is most
important to that to that particular
brain or neural network maybe in the
body that embodies it's it can move
around
has a bilateral symmetry will probably
have two arms and two legs
and all that good stuff if on the other
hand he gave me the brain of an octopus
i'll be able to tell you immediately
because they have a brain for each arm
it has an eightfold symmetry so i can
tell you a lot about the the world and
in
you know in this instance the you know
the bodily world uh from just the gross
morphometry but you can go much much
further uh i could look at your brain
and i will find two streams that emanate
from the visual parts of the brain
and i will know that they're visual
parts because your eyes are my central
nervous system and i know that they're
they're photoreceptors so i will know
that they're somehow um trying to
explain
the causes of sensations um um in a
visual scene and i will find two streams
called the dorsal and the ventral stream
that sort of run eventually in this
direction and also also in this
direction actually uh towards the
hippocampus
more eventually
here and that tells me immediately that
there's been a factorization there's
been some sort of a fundamental carving
nature at its joints in terms of the
causal architecture of this creature's
world and in particular what i will be
able to discern is you must believe that
certainly that there are
the objects have at least two attributes
um in order to um
produce their impressions of the nervous
system in the words of the helmholtz and
of course those will be what and where
and i'll be able to tell you
that you the typically the kind of
visual objects that you're trying to
explain
um
will have these two attributes that are
conditionally independent because of the
physical separation and the um
the sparse connectivity between these
two streams um so
what we're saying just in common sense
terms basically means for the typical
visual objects that we usually look at
knowing what something is doesn't tell
you where it is and
and me telling you where something is
doesn't tell you what it is so it is the
most efficient simplest minimum
complexity representation just to
represent the wholeness and awareness
and then you put them together to
explain this thing in this in this
location another nice example of
minimizing the complexity by using the
minimum degrees of freedom when carving
up the world uh you know in terms of
being a good model of that world
but you see exactly the same kind of um
if you like factorization and
effectively weight sharing in
convolutional neural networks which
brings me back to
you know don't don't be dismissive of
your cnn your favorite cnn it's got some
beautiful factorization uh in it so
the very fact that you've got this
weight sharing and this sort of
way of carving
nature at its joints um in the context
of what you see emerging convolution
your networks is that you are now saying
that there is some causal structure out
there that has local continuity or
contiguity aspects that i'm going to
leverage to provide a really simple
explanation for these kinds of data so
as soon as you tell me i'm using a cnn i
know exactly what kind of data you're
using you're using stuff that has
certain regularities in the metric space
spatially extensive uh so image-like
data if you give me another kind of
neural network that looks like a
transformer network i know you're not
doing that i know that now you're trying
to deal with things mapping one
set of categorical uh objects onto
another set of categorical objects so
just by looking at the structural form
of even i think um sort of
canonical
architectures in deep learning um you
can tell a lot about the causal
dependencies the independent the
conditional independences that generated
the kind of data that you're trying to
classify or um auto encode
i see professor this has been amazing so
the final question the last question
um
that is going to be a very non-technical
i i hope like
like a simple and nice question for to
end this talk a light question
um
that i'm sure many people watching uh
would be interested to know your opinion
about
will we ever
fully understand how the brain works
and
how far have we come at the moment
right
a simple
or is it a
[Laughter]
long
a long
difficult one i i appreciate your
attempt to ask a light a light fun
[Laughter]
and i think we've come an enormous way
and there is there is an enormous way to
go
and i think there are some principled
issues about the understandability of
ourselves that actually get into some
deep questions about consciousness and
metacognition and the kind of creatures
we are and of course the kind of curious
creatures we are and have to be in order
to exist um so i'm thinking here of um
things like david chalmer's meta problem
or met a heart problem so now in
philosophy the question has moved from
away from what is it like to be or to
see red
really why do we spend all our time
puzzling about the fact that we
can see red or experience things and of
course that speaks to this hierarchical
model
or genitive model where parts of this
genetic model now have a construct of
meanness
and meanness in particular experiential
contexts um hence the metacognitive
aspects when you think about very deep
character models so i'm sorry what does
what do you mean by meanness
oh
so you have something which you could
argue um
many um
lower forms of life possibly not dogs
and cats but sort of possibly birds
don't have
you have a part of your genitive model
is a hypothesis or a fantasy that you
are a person and that you are in charge
of orchestrating your perceptual
influence in your deep genitive models
and moving and secreting
now you don't need to have that
hypothesis or explanation in order to
function quite viably it's quite a
sophisticated being like a bird for
example but you have that which suddenly
creates the opportunity to think about
counter factual ways of me being so when
i said mean us i just meant me in
inverted commas less
yeah oh beingness sorry okay okay i i
okay okay yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah sorry
sorry yeah yeah just your question
will we ever be able to understand
ourselves i think um
it's a lovely question in the sense that
the answer to that may um hold the
secret um uh to um awareness and
particular self-awareness mean awareness
selfhood
and what particular kinds of generative
models you would have to have in order
to even ask the question um am i
yourself and then the philosopher's
question can i understand myself these
are really really very very literally
deep problems that rest about deep
hierarchical gender models
i see perfect
uh thank you so much professor fristen
it was indeed an honor to have this uh
talk with you i really enjoyed it i hope
that i didn't try uh tire you out too
much it i know it
it took a long time he did and i'm
exhausted but thrilled to have spoken to
you i really enjoyed talking to you
thank you so much thank you so much
professor and i'm truly truly sorry for
taking too much because taking too much
of your time because it's like one
interesting argument brought another one
and then it brought another one and
i apologize for that but it was a
priceless experience for me well thank
you very much you could have gone on all
night but now i i'm worried about all
your editing
well that's your problem not mine i
gotta have it exactly exactly thank you
so much have a lovely evening thank you
so much bye